Laurence Picken Papers
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Laurence Picken Papers 1900-2001 (bulk 1936-1999)
ML31.P53
Picken, Laurence Ernest Rowland
approximately 22,400 items 70 containers 38.5 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Laurence Picken was a British zoologist and musicologist who specialized in Asian, particularly Chinese, music. The collection primarily contains research materials, correspondence, writings, publications, and other items related to Picken's career and his study of East Asian musical traditions, especially those of the Tang Court. In addition, there are manuscript and published scores for Picken's musical compositions, transcriptions of traditional East Asian music, and some photographs.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Fukushima, Kazuo, 1930-; Picken, Laurence Ernest Rowland--Archives.; Picken, Laurence Ernest Rowland--Correspondence.; Picken, Laurence Ernest Rowland--Manuscripts.; Picken, Laurence Ernest Rowland--Photographs.; Picken, Laurence Ernest Rowland.; Picken, Laurence Ernest Rowland.; Picken, Laurence Ernest Rowland. Music from the Tang Court.; Picken, Laurence Ernest Rowland. Musical works. Selections.
Subjects
Music--Asia--History and criticism.; Music--China--History and criticism.; Music--East Asia.; Music--Japan--History and criticism.; Music--Manuscripts.; Musical instruments--East Asia.; Musical instruments--Turkey.; Musicologists--England.; Tōgaku.
Titles
Musica Asiatica.
Form/Genre
Articles.; Correspondence.; Drafts (Documents); Essays.; Lectures.; Notebooks.; Notes.; Photographic prints.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift, Laurence Picken, 2002.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Transfers
Sound and video recordings from the Laurence Picken Papers have been transferred to the Library of Congress Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division. An inventory of this material is available in the Music Division's collection file.
Access and Restrictions
The Laurence Picken Papers are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Music Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
British zoologist and musicologist Laurence Ernest Rowland Picken was born on July 16, 1909 in Nottingham, England. He studied piano as a child, and composed music during the mid-1920s and 1930s. In 1928, he won a scholarship to Trinity College, Cambridge and studied natural sciences. During the 1930s, he held a Rockefeller Studentship in the Geneva School of Chemistry for two years where he became fluent in French and German and conducted groundbreaking scientific research. He finished his Ph.D. in 1935. In 1944, he became a fellow at Jesus College, Cambridge, and in 1946 assistant director of research in the zoology faculty, spending the next twenty years researching and teaching biology. In 1944, he joined Joseph Needham’s scientific mission to China where he studied Chinese music and learned to play the zither. In 1959, Picken was appointed visiting professor of zoology at Washington University. He published his landmark book The Organization of Cells and other Organisms the following year in 1960.
Though employed as a scientist, Picken published his first musical paper in 1950 on the identification of an unknown fugue by Bach. His reputation as a musicologist grew along with his knowledge and understanding of Asian culture and he continued to publish papers and encyclopedia entries on Asian music throughout 1950s. Picken served as editor for the journal of the International Folk Music Council in the 1960s. In 1966, he was appointed assistant director of research in the faculty of oriental studies at Cambridge. In 1977, he started the journal Musica Asiatica which he would co-edit until 1984. Picken donated over 700 musical instruments to the Museum of Archaeology and Anthropology at Cambridge in 1977.
The music of the Chinese Tang and Song dynasties was the major focus of Picken's lifelong scholarship. In 1972, he began to transcribe and analyze pieces from the secular Tang court repertory in Japan which led to a projected 25-volume series Music from the Tang Court (1981-2000), of which Picken would complete only seven volumes. Picken also wrote on the music of Turkey, central Asia, Southeast Asia, and the Middle East. In 1975, he published The Folk Musical Instruments of Turkey, a comprehensive study of Turkish instruments. In 1990, Picken and N.J. Nickson supervised and directed a program of Tang and Song dynasty transcriptions at the Shanghai Conservatory of Music. Starting in 1998, Picken was also involved with the Ancient Asian Music Project at the Library of Congress. He died at the age of 97 on March 16, 2007, in Cambridge, England.
Scope and Content Note
The Laurence Picken Papers span the period 1900-2001 with the majority of materials dating from 1936-1999. The materials include project files, research materials, business and personal correspondence, published and unpublished writings, scores of Picken's own compositions, and photographs.
Materials in the Project Files series are centered around Picken's studies in East Asian music and range from the 1950s through the mid-1990s. These contain essay notes and drafts, translations, concert programs, miscellaneous research materials, instrument collection files, and a handful of personal files. Picken's articles and research materials for Musica Asiatica and his influential Music from the Tang Court stand out as items of particular interest. His original folder titles have been used where appropriate, although it is possible that some contain alternative or erroneous spellings and transliterations.
The Correspondence series consists of personal and business letters sent or received by Laurence Picken. Many of the letters relating to his activities discuss aspects of Picken's collaborative studies and publications between 1936 and 2001. The letters to his family include postcards from his travels abroad.
The Writings series contains articles, essays, and lectures by Picken, his notebooks, and books written for Picken. In addition, there are offprints by Picken, his students, and colleagues that were used in research. Materials in the Music series include manuscript and printed scores of Picken's compositions, dating from the 1920s and 1930s. There are also transcriptions of traditional East Asian music made by Picken and others between the 1950s and 2000. Rounding out the collection is the small Photographs series which contains images of Picken, traditional Chinese and Japanese musical instruments, and various performances of world music, dating from the 1930s to 1990s.
Organization of the Laurence Picken Papers
The Laurence Picken Papers are organized in five series:
Project Files, circa 1950-1999
Correspondence, 1900-2001
Writings, circa 1930-2000
Music, circa 1923-2000
Photographs, circa 1930-circa 1990
http://lccn.loc.gov/2011570511
Container List
- Project Files, circa 1950-1999 (Box 1-18, 64, 66)
  Chiefly research materials related to published papers and scholarly topics of interest to Picken. Includes photocopies of various original Chinese documents, drafts of publications, correspondence, and notes.
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title. Picken's original captions have been used whenever possible, although these may contain alternative or erroneous spellings of words. Article titles in the container list may not reflect those of actual published materials.
  - "Acculturation and the Tōgaku repertory" (Picken/Marett) (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Afterwards for Picken, Adkins, Page (Box-folder 1/2)
  - "An Afghan quail-lure of typological and acoustic interest" (Box-folder 9/1)
  - "Anatolian drum and shawm come to a Greek smuggler's village" (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Ancient Chinese songs (Box-folder 1/4)
  - "Ancient matters" - Koji-ruien (Box-folder 9/2)
  - Ang Kunshan (Box-folder 9/3)
  - Arthur Cooper's lecture and correspondence (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Bach quotations from the 18th Century (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Banshikichō (Box-folder 9/4)
  - Bibliographic data on key manuscripts (Box-folder 1/7)
  - British Council: "Science in Chungking" (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Bugaku (Box-folder 1/9-11)
  - Burmese music (Box-folder 1/12-13)
  - Burmese music - draft papers and correspondence with Muriel Williamson (Box-folder 9/5-6)
  - Catalogue of documents of music from the collection of the Fushimi-no-miya family (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Champa (Box-folder 10/1)
  - Ch'ao-chou requiem (Box-folder 10/2)
  - Ch'ên (Box-folder 10/3)
  - Ch'in schools (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Chiang K'uei (Box-folder 1/16-20)
  - Children's sound producing toys (Box-folder 1/21)
  - China (Box-folder 1/22)
  - Chinese Buddist music (Box-folder 1/23)
  - Chinese friction chordophones (Box-folder 1/24)
  - Chinese folksongs (Box-folder 1/25-26)
  - Chinese music (Box-folder 1/27-29)
  - Chinese texts relative to Toroden (Box-folder 1/30)
  - Chū Ōga Ryūteki Yōroku-fu (Box-folder 1/31)
  - Chuang-chên (Box-folder 10/4)
  - Concert programs (Box-folder 1/32)
  - Conflation and analysis (Box-folder 1/33)
  - Correspondence and translations by Ishibashi/Fukushima (Box-folder 2/1-2)
  - Dai Nihon shi (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Daoist white-stone [i.e. White Stone Daoist]: Jiang Kui - collected songs and pieces (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Double-sided printing of Sadachō items (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Dunhuang lute music (Rockwell) (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Dunhuang piba-pu (Box-folder 10/5)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Ethiopic liturgical music (Box-folder 2/8)
  - "The fate of Tang music in Japan" (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Fengshen Zhuan (Box-folder 2/10-12)
  - "Finger techniques for the zithers sô-no-koto and kin in Heian times" (Mitani/Picken) (Box-folder 2/13, 10/6)
  - First transcriptions of Meiji and Shōwa printed shō tablatures (Box-folder 10/7)
  - Fragments of Fengxue (Box-folder 3/14)
  - "Frequency doubling chordophones" (Adkins/Williams/Flowers/Picken) (Box-folder 3/15)
  - Fujiwara genealogies (Box-folder 3/16)
  - "The functional names of notes in Modai note-sets" (Box-folder 3/17-18)
  - Gagaku (Box-folder 11/1)
  - Gagaku (Harich-Schneider) (Box-folder 11/2)
  - Gakka-roku (excerpts) (Box-folder 2/19)
  - Gidayu (Box-folder 2/20)
  - Gogenfu (copy of F.R.W.'s transcripts) (Box-folder 2/21)
  - GoGen Kin-Fu (Box-folder 11/3)
  - Notes on gougche-pu derived from Yang YenLin and Zhang Shipeng (Box-folder 2/22)
  - Guan's comments on Tōgaku titles in Hakuga nofue-fu (Box-folder 2/23)
  - Haloun: notes for the burning of the books (Box-folder 2/24)
  - Hayashi Kenzō (Box-folder 11/4)
  - Hirade (Box-folder 2/25)
  - Honorary doctorate, 1988 (Box-folder 2/26-27)
  - Hosho-fu (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Hōshō ritsu-kan (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Hyōjō (Box-folder 11/5)
  - Ichikotsuchō (Box-folder 12/1)
  - Instrument collection (Box-folder 3/3)
  - "The instrumentarium of a village in Northeast Thailand" (Box-folder 12/2)
  - Jao Tsung-I preface, 1990 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Japanese historical linguistics (Box-folder 3/5)
  - JCYR (Box-folder 12/3)
  - "Jew's harps and mouth organs" (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Jiang Kui (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Jiaofang-ji (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Jiegulu (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Jinchi-yoroku (Box-folder 64/1)
  - Junior sinologues (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Kaichū-fu (Box-folder 3/11-12)
  - "A keyboard fugue by Bach" (Box-folder 3/13-14)
  - Kikutei: "Pieces for biwa, notated in calendrically correct tunings, from the Kikutei-ke Monjo of the Heian Hakubutsukan" (Box-folder 3/15)
  - Ko-fu ritsu (Box-folder 3/16)
  - Korean court dance under Sejong and Sejo (Box-folder 13/1-2)
  - Kucha music influence (Box-folder 3/17)
  - Kunaichō shoryōbu (Box-folder 3/18)
  - Kyōkun shō (Box-folder 3/19)
  - Libo songs in Gi-shi Gakufu (Box-folder 13/3)
  - Library of Congress exhibition, 1999 (Box-folder 3/20-22, 13/4)
  - "A lion dance of the Song Dynasty" (Box-folder 3/23)
  - Mabuchi Usaburō (Box-folder 3/24)
  - "The magic of children's sound-producing toys" (Box-folder 3/25)
  - Mahmut Ragip Gazimihal (Box-folder 3/26)
  - "Making a Khaein" (Adkins/Page/Picken) (Box-folder 3/27)
  - Marett transcription of Chōkōraku (Box-folder 3/28)
  - Material from "Ancient echos of China" (Box-folder 3/29)
  - "Midnight music" (Yebanyue) (Box-folder 3/30)
  - Miscellaneous articles (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Miscellaneous materials in Chinese (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Miscellaneous music in Chinese (Box-folder 14/1, 64/2)
  - Miscellaneous research materials, Includes appendices, bibliographies, examples, figures, and various documents in Chinese (Box-folder 4/3-24, 14/2-4, 64/3)
  - Mongolian articles (Box-folder 4/25)
  - "Music for a lion-dance" of the Song Dynasty (Box-folder 4/26)
  - Music of the Tang Court (Box-folder 5, 6/1-11, 15, 64/4-5)
  - Music Research Institute of Chicago (Peking) (Box-folder 4/27)
  - Musica Asiatica articles (Box-folder 6/12-21)
  - "Musical implications of Chinese songtext with unequal lines and the significance of nonsense syllables, with special reference to artsongs of Song Dynasty" (Box-folder 6/22, 14/5)
  - "Musical inter-relationships between Tang Chinese compositions; Three items with titles in the names of imperial military leaders" (Box-folder 6/23)
  - Musikethnologische Jahresbibliographie Europas (Box-folder 6/24)
  - Namguan (Box-folder 16/1)
  - Namguan Patsy Choo (Box-folder 6/25)
  - Nawa contents (Box-folder 6/26)
  - Neopolitan cries (Box-folder 6/27)
  - Notes (Box-folder 6/28-29)
  - Notes on Hichiriki scores: Nakahara-roseishō and others (Box-folder 6/30)
  - Notes on mensural notation in Ō-dai (Box-folder 6/31)
  - Notes on mouth organ scoring (Box-folder 6/32)
  - Notes on music manuscripts purhcased by Elling Eide (Box-folder 6/33)
  - "Notes on some important Togaku manuscripts in Tenri University Library" (Box-folder 16/2)
  - Notes on tablature system of Kofu/Hōshōfu (Ritsu/Ryokan) (Box-folder 6/34)
  - Ojikichō (Box-folder 16/3)
  - Okugaki (Box-folder 7/1)
  - Personalia and CV (Box-folder 7/2)
  - Pipa techniques and terms (Box-folder 7/3)
  - Pipafu (Box-folder 7/4)
  - Picken Collection of Musical Instruments, Cambridge University Museum of Archaeology and Ethnology, Two-volume card index (Box 66)
  - Picken donations (Box-folder 7/5)
  - Picken library (Box-folder 7/6)
  - Picken's criticism of Robert T. Mok's "Ancient musical instruments unearthed from the number one Han tomb at Ma Want Tui, Changsha" (Box-folder 7/7)
  - Plainsong notes (Box-folder 7/8)
  - The 'plucked drums' (Box-folder 7/9)
  - Porcelain (Box-folder 7/10)
  - Publication agreements (Box-folder 7/11)
  - R.H. van Gulik's bronze (Box-folder 7/12)
  - Qui Jingsun (Box-folder 17/1)
  - Radio talk / Chinese 7-string zither (Box-folder 7/13)
  - Rakusaidō Gagaku manuscripts (Kazuo Fukushima) (Box-folder 7/14)
  - Reviews and acknowledgements (Box-folder 7/15)
  - Reviews by Laurence Picken (Box-folder 7/16)
  - Revue bibliographique de sinologie (Box-folder 7/17)
  - Ruisō-chiyō (Box-folder 7/18-20)
  - Ryō-ō (Box-folder 17/2)
  - Ryūmeishō (Box-folder 7/21-22)
  - Samaifu glossary and definitions (Box-folder 7/23)
  - Samaifu copy of Maifu of Shunnōden, Satto and Juha (Box-folder 7/24)
  - Sandai jitsuroku (Box-folder 7/25)
  - Sango-yōroku (Box-folder 7/26)
  - Second Samaifu copy from Tsuji sensei (Box-folder 7/27)
  - Secret dragon flute score (Box-folder 17/3)
  - Semsi Yastiman (Box-folder 7/28)
  - SGYR (Box-folder 17/4)
  - Shanghai Conservatory (Box-folder 7/29)
  - "The shapes of the Shi Jing song texts and their musical implications" (Box-folder 64/8)
  - Shi Jing (Box-folder 7/30)
  - Shi Jing paper (Musica Asiatica, 1977) (Box-folder 17/7)
  - Shinnō hajinraku (Box-folder 17/5-6)
  - Shinraryō-ō Sairyōshū (Box-folder 7/31)
  - Shō and Bisa part parallelism (Shō part is cantus firmus) (Box-folder 18/1)
  - Song texts (Box-folder 7/32)
  - Sōnokoto tunings (Box-folder 7/33)
  - The sound of Areston (Gershevitch) (Box-folder 18/2)
  - "The sound producing instrumentarium of a village in North-East Thailand" (Box-folder 7/34)
  - Specimen tune in all Chinese modes at same pitch, both pentatonic and heptatonic (Box-folder 7/35)
  - "String/table angles in harps, from the third millenium BC to the present" (Box-folder 7/36)
  - Taigenshō Kyō Kunshō (Box-folder 7/37-38)
  - Taiheiraku (Box-folder 18/3, 7/39)
  - T'ang dance notation (Box-folder 7/40)
  - Taoist ritual music (Box-folder 7/41)
  - Teheran congress 1961 (Box-folder 7/42)
  - Thai mouth organs, correspondence with Peter Bee papers (Box-folder 7/43)
  - Thai music "The making of a Rhāen" correspondence (Box-folder 7/44)
  - Tōdai-ji Yōroku Kaigen-e (Box-folder 7/45)
  - Tōgaku pieces transcribed (Box-folder 7/46)
  - Toyonaga Satomi papers (Box-folder 7/47)
  - Transcriptions from Festival of GI (Box-folder 8/1-3)
  - "Tunes of T'ang date for the 'get trasure song'?" (Jones/Picken) (Box-folder 8/4)
  - Tunings and pitch measurements (Ruttner) (Box-folder 8/5)
  - Turkey (Box-folder 8/6)
  - Turkish reviews and letters (Box-folder 8/7)
  - Tweleve ritual melodies of the T'ang Dynasty (Box-folder 8/8)
  - 'Ulili (Box-folder 8/9)
  - Utsucho - Monogatari; also copy of Noguchi's paper on Utsucho-Monogatari (Box-folder 8/10)
  - "Water birds on river islands" (Box-folder 8/11)
  - Wang Zhaojun (Box-folder 8/12)
  - Wamyō ruijūshō (Box-folder 8/13)
  - "The war of the musicians or lives of canonised spirits of the Taoist Heaven" (Zhu Chanyu) (Box-folder 8/14)
  - Wei-shi Yuepu (Box-folder 8/15)
  - Xeroxes of small books (Box-folder 8/16)
  - Yuefu (Box-folder 8/17)
  - Yuefu shiqi - song structure, length and rhymes (Box-folder 8/18)
  - Yuefu zalu (Box-folder 8/19)
  - YFST (Box-folder 8/20-22)
  - Zhong Yang, Yin Yue, Xue Yuan, Xue Bao (Box-folder 8/23)
  - Zhu Xi (Box-folder 8/24)
  - Zoku-Kyōkunshō (Box-folder 8/25)
  - Zokukoto: Rokudan no shirabe nofu (Box-folder 8/26)
- Correspondence, 1900-2001 (Box 19-52)
  Chiefly letters concerning scholarly projects, family matters, and travel.
  Arranged in four subseries: letters to Picken; letters from Picken; family correspondence; and related correspondence. Each subseries arranged chronologically.
  - Letters to Picken
    - 1935-1971 (Box-folder 19/1-7)
    - 1972-1975 (Box-folder 20/1-8)
    - 1976-1981 (Box-folder 21/1-12)
    - 1982-1987 (Box-folder 22/1-9)
    - 1992 (Box-folder 23/1-8)
    - 1993-1994 (Box-folder 24/1-6)
    - 1995-1996 (Box-folder 25/1-7)
    - 1997 (Box-folder 26/1-4)
    - 1998 (Box-folder 27/1-7)
    - 1999-2001 (Box-folder 28/1-9)
    - Foreign language letters, 1968-1998 (Box-folder 29/1)
    - Undated (Box-folder 29/2, 30/1-2)
  - Letters from Picken
    - 1936-1972 (Box-folder 31/1-7)
    - 1973-1975 (Box-folder 32/1-6)
    - 1975-1976 (Box-folder 33/1-6)
    - 1977 (Box-folder 34/1-5)
    - 1978-1979 (Box-folder 35/1-7)
    - 1979-1980 (Box-folder 36/1-6)
    - 1981-1982 (Box-folder 37/1-6)
    - 1982-1983 (Box-folder 38/1-6)
    - 1984 (Box-folder 39/1-6)
    - 1985 (Box-folder 40/1-6)
    - 1986 (Box-folder 41/1-4)
    - 1987 (Box-folder 42/1-4)
    - 1988-1989 (Box-folder 43/1-8)
    - 1990-1991 (Box-folder 44/1-9)
    - 1992 (Box-folder 45/1-4)
    - 1993 (Box-folder 46/1-5)
    - 1994-1995 (Box-folder 47/1-8)
    - 1996 (Box-folder 47/9-10)
    - 1997-1998 (Box-folder 48/1-7)
    - 1999-2001 and undated (Box-folder 49/1-9)
  - Family Correspondence
    - Family to Picken, 1939-1945 (Box-folder 50/1-2)
    - Picken to family, 1950-1990s (Box-folder 51/1-11)
  - Related Correspondence
    - 1900-2001 and undated (Box-folder 52/1-8)
- Writings, circa 1930-2000 (Box 53-57, 67-70)
  Articles, essays, lectures, and notebooks. Most materials have accompanying correspondence and notes. Includes offprints of works by various authors (including Picken) used in the course of research.
  Arranged in five subseries: lectures; notebooks; papers edited by Picken; offprints about Chinese music; and books written for Picken. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically by title, author, or subject.
  - Lectures
    - Chinese music (Box-folder 53/1-2)
    - "Chinese music of a thousand years ago" (Box-folder 53/3)
    - "A comparative journey of the musics of the world" (Box-folder 53/4)
    - "The documentary history of the Tōgaku repertory" (Box-folder 53/5)
    - "Micro-ornament" (Box-folder 53/6)
    - Miscellaneous lectures (Box-folder 53/7)
    - "Music aspects of transcription and analysis of the Tōgaku repertory" (Box-folder 53/11)
    - "Music at the Tang Court" (Hume) (Box-folder 53/8)
    - "Music for a Tang Dynasty ballet of the 7th century" (Box-folder 53/9)
    - "Music from the Tang Court" (Saibara) (Box-folder 53/10)
    - "A musical background to treasures of Ancient China" (Box-folder 53/12)
    - "Musical instruments in Turkey" (Box-folder 53/13)
    - "Musical survivals of the Tang and Sung Dynasties" (Box-folder 53/14)
    - Seoul, South Korea (Box-folder 53/15)
    - "Tang music of the Sung Dynasty" (Box-folder 53/16)
    - "Towards the archaic music of pre-Nora Japan" (Box-folder 53/17)
    - "Turkish folk music and musical instruments" (Box-folder 53/18)
    - "Turkish music" (Box-folder 53/19)
    - "Turkish poetry" (Box-folder 53/20)
    - University of Washington, Seattle (Box-folder 53/21-23)
    - Unidentified (Box-folder 53/14)
  - Notebooks
    - Asian Music Club (Box-folder 53/25)
    - Asian notebooks, 1972-1974, 1980 (Box-folder 54/1, 67/1-3)
    - Biographical notebook, Chiefly business cards, pamphlets, and photographs (Box-folder 67/4)
    - Buddhist music (Box-folder 67/5)
    - Ch'au-chou requiem service (Box-folder 67/6)
    - Chinese and Sino-Japanese notebooks (Box-folder 53/26)
    - Miscellaneous notebooks (Box-folder 53/27-28, 68/1)
    - Taoist music (Box-folder 68/2)
    - Tōgaku notebooks: draft catalogue of pieces, movements, and occurrence in manuscripts (Box-folder 53/29-30)
    - Turkish notebooks (Box-folder 68/3-5, 69/1-5)
  - Papers Edited by Picken
    - Blench, Roger. "The morphology and distribution of Sub-Saharan musical instruments of North African, Middle Eastern, and Asian origin" (Box-folder 54/2)
    - Craig, Dale A. "Ancient legacy of music: a Min Dynasty collection of Chin songs" (Box-folder 54/3-4)
    - Fletcher, Peter. World musics in context (Box-folder 54/5)
    - Fukushima, Kazuo. "Descriptive catalogue of the Rakusaidō-Gagaku manuscripts in the Research Archives for Japanese Music of Ueno Gakuen College" (Box-folder 54/6)
    - Marett, Allan J., Miscellaneous essays and draft of dissertation (Box-folder 54/7-9)
    - Miyoko, Kôkawa. "A method of improvising music at school" (Box-folder 54/10)
    - Wei, Deng. "Historical and stylistic development in the Chinese four-stringed lute Pipa and in Pipa music" (Box-folder 54/11-12)
    - Widdess, Richard. "The reconstruction of early Indian music from notation" (Box-folder 54/13)
    - Williamson, Muriel C. "The correlation between speech-tones of text-syllables and their musical settings in a Burmese classical song" (Box-folder 54/14)
  - Offprints about Chinese Music
    - 1936-1975, Four bound volumes of Picken's articles; Includes several earlier articles on cellular biology (Box 70)
    - "A" - "C" (Box-folder 54/15-19)
    - "D" - "Picard" (Box-folder 55/1-19)
    - "Picken" - "Z" (Box-folder 56/1-16)
  - Books Written for Picken
    - Three bound essays in honor of Dr. Laurence E. R. Picken (Box 57)
- Music, circa 1923-2000 (Box 58-62, 65)